Arriving in Morocco felt like a dream at first.
An oasis of peace, rest and food. Oh, the food!
Now I could finally understand my mother. Why would you choose not to eat food when you know that tomorrow there may be none?
I blissfully ate and ate, greedily regrowing my strength, chatting happily with the other travellers.
I was so happy that it took me a while to realise how some native birds were looking at us.
The great ibises, the mighty cormorans, the graceful flamingos.
They didn’t talk to us, but I could see disapproval in their eyes. I couldn’t understand why.
And then one day, I was drinking by the lake when I saw a woodpecker looking at me.
“Don’t you think you have overstayed your welcome?” He sneered.
“What do you mean?” I asked.
“You know what I mean. You are coming here in flocks, eating our food, drinking our water, taking over our woods by millions, making them dirty and unsafe. Don’t you know you are not welcome here?”
I was stunned, I didn’t know what to answer. Nobody had ever talked to me like that.
Then I heard another voice behind me.
“Don’t take this personally, it will happen again.”
That bird was my age, I had seen him before, but we had never spoken.
“How do you know?” I asked.
“I’ve done the journey once. It was tough, but you’ll get used to it, bird.”
“Don’t call me bird” I said. “My name is Mawusi.”
“Sure. That’s a nice name, but you know that nobody will ever be able to be able to pronounce it, right?
I’m Banjoko, but I got used to people calling me Bird.
You’ll see, when you get there, nobody will remember your name, nobody will care if you are a swallow, a sand martin, a willow warbler.
It’s all the same to them, to them you will be just another bird.
I don’t think it comes from a bad place. They just don’t know foreign birds very well.”
I didn’t reply.
“So” he said “I think that woodpecker was pretty clear, it seems like we have overstayed our welcome. Are you ready for the next part of the trip, Bird?”